so thanks so much for talking to us uh
jason um very much enjoyed uh speaking
to you as part of the
the wider group um i have a number of
questions that i'd like to follow up on
uh following your your your talk
um the first the first of these
questions is so you're currently the
associate professor in the department of
sociology at durham shortly heading
towards the university of glasgow to
take up a professorship
uh could you tell us about some of the
you know the real defining moments of
your career
that's a great question and
i would say
the most defining moment or something
really fun is when i got my phd
so i completed my phd in two and a half
years working full-time
so like i i killed myself to do it but
the reason why it was really significant
um which which i've i've said i've said
publicly now sometimes i'll say it but
like um i had it at the time i had a
brain tumor
um uh
and i had my brain tumor removed
two weeks
two weeks before i had my viva so i
didn't remember anything so i had a
stroke straight after so um
like um passing that was really really
significant because i never know
how far
i got across the line
or not what the most important things i
got across the line so like um
that was that was a really really
significant thing because uh
literally speaking i just became a dad
for the second time
and if that and my job at the time was
dependent upon me getting um
my phd and i haven't got it i would have
made redundant so that was really
important
and then guessing that there are there
are several things but i guess probably
the biggest thing was when i got my job
at durham
um because i'd been knocking on the door
a long time
and i decided that like um you know if i
didn't get that particular job
um having had quite a lot of heartbreak
i thought um i i was actually gonna take
a job working in city hall um
as a
as a research analyst in um in khan's
office
so that's what i would have done um i
would have applied for that and i think
i would have had a good chance of
getting it and so i had an interview so
i would have
um that's where i would have gone
um i'm glad it all worked out so uh
it sounds like an amazingly
stressful time uh
two children
a brain tumor
uh a phd and a new job uh
my goodness me that was a very busy time
of your life for sure yeah nice very
defining
yeah it was yes i was 2015 and then 2019
was when i had the interview in april
and um
yeah and i remember getting the news it
was
it was just really all right
it felt like i'd finally realized any
potential that i i may have thought i
humbly had and
it was a huge relief to do that and from
that point on that's when i really
thought like it was on in terms of like
you know we could make this happen you
know you could become a professor like
um
and and then i just went for it from
from 2019 really went through it
excellent
so the sec the second question that i've
got from you is so you've written about
the difficulties that are faced by
black doctoral students pursuing a
career in academia
could you tell us more about the
research that you've done in this space
and what you see as the main barriers uh
what the main barriers are and what
action needs to be taken so what can we
do
that's great so
yeah so i i think a lot of the research
i've done is kind of really around
unearthing
black and ethnic minority experiences
and people from particular class
background particularly working class
with an insect as well and i guess my
research is kind of really pointed or is
moved towards in the last two or three
years around the impact on psychological
well-being
so you know what's the impact of
experiencing inequality across the
intersection particularly within the
context of race
on kind of how people
ex you know how how did they navigate
these experiences and what is the
residual effect was all the kind of
psychological scarring but um
that happens as a result of kind of
experiencing these uh discriminations so
a lot of my research has been around
that and really kind of unpacking
how we develop better systems to better
support people who experience racial
trauma
and obviously that's going to cross the
intersection a lot of my work now is
looking at the experience i've looked
after children
as well
in terms of how i looked after children
navigate the education system and the
lack of opportunities they have in doing
that so a lot of the time there's always
this idea around how do we mobilize um
these different types of inequality
so we recognize the problem but then we
kind of really think about how we work
with organizations to create something
different so you know i was really
fortunate to work with the nhs
in terms of developing or advising on um
training for
therapists and counselors
in terms of being racially cognizant and
racially literate and recognizing the
impact of that and as part of that work
i had to qualify i qualified as a
counselor
two and a half years ago so that i could
do have some credibility doing this work
and so that was kind of really important
in terms of kind of learning about that
and more importantly how we better
inform
people and support people who present
mental health
um or mental illness at particular
stages because we know historically
black and ethnic minority people
intergenerationally have been um
pretty poorly served
by uh the mental health system in the uk
so we don't we don't often work towards
cognitive behavioral therapies or
psychological therapies we often move
towards medication straight away for
people of color and so i really wanted
to kind of challenge that and do
research that complemented people who
were experts in the area and someone
that had an interest who then wants to
become an expert in the area
that's excellent so we need to think
about um we need to figure out
structures there's obviously a training
piece as part of that as well sort of
training the people who have that kind
of
that kind of contact directly and
educating them
with with sort of first-hand experience
which in many cases they don't have
so my last question is you've produced a
report on with the black curriculum
interest group to address the lack of
black
history in the uk curriculum
uh how do you think the lack of black uh
british history being taught in schools
has affected us affected young black
children and their aspirations
that's a really good question i don't
think it's affected their aspirations
because i think in spite of that absence
black children continue to defy the odds
and do exceptional things passing
through
the educational pipeline in terms of
primary secondary further education and
into higher education as the numbers
reflect
but i think in terms of um being a whole
person and recognizing the impact of
your own histories on
you know
empire and the contribution of you know
indigenous populations and black
populations and minority ethnic
populations and diasporas
on these things i think it's it's
important because i think the sole
purpose of education to prepare people
to take their place within society now
the way that we do that is we're
providing people these skill sets these
cultures these understandings of the
world that allow us to truly be global
citizens and i think in depriving
um
black children and ethnic minority
children of that history you are you are
you are taking away
um their currency intergenerationally in
this world and i think that's really
really important that we think about how
we do that but not only recognize the
benefit of it for black and ethnic
minority children recognize the benefit
of it for all children because we want
all children to be global citizens and
be as prepared as they can to take their
place within society in the absence of
that cultural understanding and that
historic understanding that kind of
resides in this historical amnesia and
that we reside in where we completely
obscure
the kind of contribution of black and
ethnic minority people beyond
subordinating an enslaved means or
oppressed means means that we're not
preparing people to one change the
stereotypes to have with people and to
preparing them to actually go into a
world where you have to
engage with multi-ethnic multi-diverse
populations so we're failing not only
white children
denying black children failing white
children as well
by not preparing them to take their
placement society into having this
knowledge
yeah absolutely history's such a
powerful thing it with history we can we
can learn and and obviously that can can
educate the next generation next
generations and so we don't make the
same sorts of mistakes again
uh thank you so much jason that was
fabulous and uh i really enjoyed talking
to you today oh david thank you so much
for the opportunity i really appreciate
it and i really hope everyone has a
great day thank you